A Guide to the John L. Heatwole Collection 1802-1901
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
John L. Heatwole Collection 1802-1901
Special Collections, James Madison University
2040
This collection contains 4 folders.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated to Carrier Library by John L. Heatwole of Bridgewater, Va., on several occasions beginning in December, 1987.
Biographical/Historical Information
not given
Scope and Content
This collection consists of legal and business documents from Rockingham, Augusta, and Page Counties from 1802 to 1901. It also contains herbal recipes and other documents used by the donor in his 1995 book, Shenandoah Voices. The collector's theme was to acquire documents that, by virtue of the person who signed it, or the letterhead it bore, or the printer, or the location of the event, or some other characteristic, had distinct and particular significance to Shenandoah Valley history. Accompanying the collection are notes by the donor on most of the individual documents.
Arrangement
Materials are in chronological order.
Contents List
- Green Valley and Page County Documents 1802-1901 (Folder 1 and 2)
  - Arrest warrent for Jacob Cherryholmes for swearing "three profain oaths." 1802
  - Order for the seizure of goods of George Pence for non-payment of a debt. 1802
  - Dry River Road petition. 1807
    One of the signers is Samuel Gilmore who was badly wounded by broadsword and bayonet at the Battle pf Waxhaws, South Carolina on May 29, 1780. The battle has also been called Buford's Defeat (after the American Commander) and Colonel Tarleton's Massacre (after the British Commander).
  - Indenture of George and Joseph Hamilton and James Anderson to Samuel Henry in Rockingham County. 1808
  - Indenture of James Smily to John Carthrea in Rockingham County. 1808
  - Bond between David Thompson and Henry Smith on one part and Asher Waterman Sheriff of Rockingham County. 1809
  - Note of obligation "printed by Jacob D. Dietrick." Dietrick(h) was one of the first valley printers, first in Winchester, then in Staunton. 1809
  - Summons issued for Aaron Gains. 1809
  - List of Rockingham County court cases of interest to Augusta County officials. 1810
    It is signed by Judge John McDowell and attorney Chapman Johnson who served in the Virginia Senate and House of Delegates and was one of the most respected lawyers in Western Virginia. He was born in Louisa County in 1779.
  - Order for the seizure or goods of George Pants and Paul (?) for non-payment of a debt. 1811
  - Road Petition for "We the Naked Creek people." Eastern Rockingham County. 1811
  - Document signed by Justice Asher Waterman. 1812
    Waterman had been a surgeon for the Continental Army during the Revolutionary War. Later he owned and sold thousands of acres of land in western Rockingham County.
  - Estate receipt. Rockingham County. 1817
  - Document signed by John Crummy as a Justice of the Peace for Rockingham County. 1818
    He is holding a hearing at the tavern of Thomas Lanahan to hear a complaint against a barney ward brought by another Harrisonburg tavern keeper, James Duff. Crummy was a gunsmith by trade.
  - Virginia tax receipt. Orange County. 1827
  - Greenville lots tax receipts. 1834
  - List of 1836 tax levy showing 4645 tithables. 1836
  - Legal receipt of John Newton. 1841
  - Document signed by Wm. Robertson, a Virginia state senator in the 1840s. 1845
  - Document authorizing a payment to the Rockingham County jailer, Peter Irick, for repairs he has made to the jail. It is signed by Henry Gambill, the clerk of county court. 1847
  - Complaint filed by William Brown against Zachariah Raines. 1857
    Raines was known as the Commodore of the Shenandoah River Fleet. He organized and led the flatboat flotillas down the Shenandoah River to Harper's Ferry in the early 19th century.
  - Tax receipt signed by John Newton, Agent for C.H. McCormick of Augusta County. 1861
  - Notice of debt to Joseph Salyards by George Petty. 1868
  - Document signed by Joseph Salyards, considered by many to be the most learned man in the Valley prior to the Civil War. 1870
  - Documents signed by James Kerr Edmondson. 1889
    He was Colonel of the 27th Virginia Infantry Regiment (Stonewall Brigade) during the Civil War. He lost his left arm on May 3, 1863 at the Battle of Chancellorsville. Later he served as Mayor of Lexington, Virginia.
  - Business letterhead. The Harrisonburg Steam Pottery Company. 1896
    The company was founded by Emanual Suter who was trained before the Civil War as a folk potter. This is in his handwriting.
  - Business letterhead. S.H. Heatwole Eureka Roller Mills. 1896
  - Business letterhead. C.H. Eshman Fine Cigars, Harrisonburg, Virginia. 1897
  - Business letterhead. Bridgewater Manufacturing Company. 1901
    This was located where Wildwood Park now stands.
- Zigler Documents 1828-1850 (Folder 3)
  recepits for muster fines and orders granting Private Entertainment to John or David Zigler of Timberville, VA, 1828-1850. Purchased by donor at Zigler auction ca. 1989.
- Recipes (Folder 4)
  2 printed and 2 handwritten recipes for herbal cures and for gunpowder, with explanatory notes by donor.